[
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 1,
        "year": 2013,
        "question": "<p>(a) Describe the term Government as an art of governing</p><p>(b) Highlight any four duties of government </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong>(a)</strong> The term Government as an art of governing refers to the methods and processes involved in the formulation and implementation of public policies.</p><p><strong>(b)</strong> (i) To make laws for peace and good governance.</p><p>(ii) To administer justice through amicable settlement of disputes.</p><p>(iii) To provide infrastructure/social services for the people e.g construction, maintenance of roads, etc.</p><p>(iv) To defend and protect the lives and properties of its citizens.</p><p>(v) To protect the Fundamental Human Rights e.g. right to life, property, etc</p><p>(vi) To maintain external relations with other countries.</p><p>(vii) To enforce/implement laws and policies upon the people.</p><p>(viii) To provide and enhance the provision of employment opportunities.</p><p>(ix) To maintain law and order.</p><p>(x) To raise public revenue</p><p>(xi) To promote and protect national interest</p><p>(xii) To organize and conduct elections and population census. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 2,
        "year": 2013,
        "question": "<p>(a) Explain de-concentration of power</p><p>(b) Outline any five importance of decentralization</p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong>(a)</strong> De-concentration of power refers to a model/system of administration in which political powers are shared in such a way that the component units (States/Regions) are not directly subordinate to the central authority. The component units derive their powers and authorities from the constitution.</p><p><strong>(b)</strong> (i) De-concentration tends to mobilize the grassroots for national development.</p><p>(ii) it gives room for quick response to local needs.</p><p>(iii) it protects the interest of minority groups</p><p>(iv) it reduces the volume of work at the national level, thus promoting efficiency</p><p>(v) it encourages wider participation by the local people in government affairs</p><p>(vi) it encourages and taps local initiatives.</p><p>(viii) it promotes healthy competition among the various local units.</p><p>(ix) it provides a training ground for political leadership from the grassroots.</p><p>(x) it enhances the making of diverse laws by the component units</p><p>(xi) it brings government nearer to the people.</p><p>(xii) it provides for wide consultation e.g constitutional amendment </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 3,
        "year": 2013,
        "question": "<p>(a) What is constitution?</p><p>(b) Why do some countries use written constitutions?</p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong>(a)</strong> A constitution refers to a whole body of fundamental laws, customs, conventions, principles, rules and regulations according to which a particular country is governed.</p><p><strong>(b) </strong>(i) A written constitution can be obtained and consulted as a single document</p><p>(ii) it enhances reference in cases of disputes</p><p>(iii) Both educated and laymen can reach it.</p><p>(iv) it removes uncertainty normally experienced with unwritten constitution.</p><p>(v) it can amended or changed by following appropriate procedures.</p><p>(vi) it makes it easy to ascertain unconstitutional act.</p><p>(vii) it makes it easy for citizens to know when their rights are violated</p><p>(viii) it clearly defines the power and functions of each organ of government.</p><p>(ix) it prevents the possible emergence of dictatorship.</p><p>(x) it ensues stability especially in pluralistic societies.</p><p>(xi) it acts as a tangible and symbolic value for the nation.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 4,
        "year": 2013,
        "question": "<p>(a) Explain concurrent functions in a federation</p><p>(b) Outline five features of a confederal system of government.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a) Concurrent functions are powers and functions jointly exercised by both the federal, state/ regional governments but in the case of conflicts in discharging these duties, the power of the federal government will prevail over the state/regional governments.</p><p>(b) (i) A confederal system of government has a very weak Centre</p><p> (ii) The confederating States are nearly autonomous.</p><p>(iii) Secession of any component unit is constitutionally allowed.</p><p>(iv) Component units to develop at their own pace.</p><p>(v) Citizens' allegiance is more to the component units than to the confederation.</p><p>(vi) Component units co-operate on specific areas such as foreign affairs, currency and defense.</p><p>(vii) Exclusive legislative lists are reserved to the confederating units.</p><p>(viii) Each confederating unit retains its identity.</p><p>(ix) The confederacy depends on financial contributions from the confederating units. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 5,
        "year": 2013,
        "question": "<p>Describe the organizational structure of a political party.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(i) Ward branches - smallest unit of the party structure - official chairman, secretary and treasurer.</p><p>(ii) Local government branches</p><p>(iii) Constituency branches - including a chairman, organizing secretary, treasurer etc.</p><p>(iv) Affiliated bodies</p><p>(v)Regional/State branches - coordinate the activities of all constituency branches.</p><p>(vi) National Conference responsible for National Delegates Conference</p><p>(vii) National Working Committee</p><p>(viii) National Secretariat</p><p>(ix) National Executive Committee</p><p>(x) Board of Trusties</p><p>(xi) General Convention or Congress </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 6,
        "year": 2013,
        "question": "<p>Outline any six functions of the Emir in the Hausa/Fulani traditional political system </p>",
        "answer": "<p>(i) The Emir made laws over the areas under his jurisdiction.</p><p>(ii) He appointed other officials in the Emirate like Madawaki, Waziri, Mogaji, etc</p><p>(iii) He maintained law and order within his Emirate through the local policemen</p><p>(iv) He performed spiritual functions as the spiritual leader of the Emirate</p><p>(v) He organised his people for communal works. (vi) He imposed and collected taxes like Kharaji, Jangali, etc</p><p>(vii) He presided over the Emir's court as a judge</p><p>(viii) He organised his people for the defence of the Emirate through Madawaki, the commander of the cavalry</p><p>(ix) He honoured brave warriors and conferred traditional titles on notable citizens.</p><p>(x) Acted as a link between his people and other communities.</p><p>(xi) He performed ceremonial functions.</p><p>(xii) He preserved the culture and tradition of the people</p><p>(xiii) He shared war booties</p><p>(xiv) He maintained a strong standing army</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 7,
        "year": 2013,
        "question": "<p>Explain the importance of the Brazzaville Conference of 1944 in the constitutional development of French West Africa</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(i) The aim of the Brazzaville Conference was to determine the future relationship between France and her colonies and also to determine the lines along which the colonies should develop.</p><p>(ii) It was there that agreement was reached for African colonies to send their representatives to the first and second Constituent Assemblies in Paris.</p><p>(iii) The Conference decided that colonies should have Local Assemblies or Legislatures with African and French representatives.</p><p>(iv) It was agreed at the Conference that African culture, condemned originally, be left intact.</p><p>(v) French citizenship should be extended to all Africans.</p><p>(vi) The indigenous Policy which was used to clamp down on all opposition to the French colonial rule was abolished.</p><p>(vii) The Conference recommended autonomy of various units</p><p>(viii) The Conference also abolished forced labour </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 8,
        "year": 2013,
        "question": "<p>Highlight four factors that led to the collapse of the West African Students' Union (WASU) before the end of the Second World War.</p>",
        "answer": "<p> (i) The West African Students' Union was not very much linked with the ordinary West African peoples as they centred most of their activities in London instead of West African towns and villages.</p><p>(ii) It was an elite group which was seeking benefits for its members</p><p>(iii) In the mid-1930s the trend of nationalism had shifted from inter-territorial to national to national consciousness in British West Africa.</p><p>(iv) It was a proto-nationalist movement and its method of operation was seen as conservativ e which did not appeal to the people in West Africa.</p><p>(v) It faced hierarchical/leadership difficulties.</p><p>(vii) Ineffective organisational mechanisms</p><p>(viii) Inadequate funding </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 9,
        "year": 2013,
        "question": "<p>Give any six reasons for the breakdown of the Macpherson Constitution of 1951</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(i) The constitution encouraged regional division and ethnic nationalism. This discouraged politicians from cooperating for the success of the constitution</p><p>(ii) The regional representatives were more loyal to their respective regions rather than the centre where they operated.</p><p>(iii) The absence of the prime minister's office to coordinate the affairs of the country.</p><p>(iv) The nationalists disliked the veto power being used by the Governor</p><p>(v) The constitution created ministerial positions without giving the appointed Ministers full control over their respective ministries</p><p>(vi) The NCNC and AG sponsored motion for independence in 1953 weakened the parliament</p><p>(vii) The kano Riot of 1953 led to bitterness between the North and South.</p><p>(viii) The Eastern Regional Crisis of 1953</p><p>(ix) The absence of the three political party leaders in the central parliament</p><p>(x) Absence of a uniform electoral system </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 10,
        "year": 2013,
        "question": "<p> (a) Explain the term Indirect Rule</p><p>(b) Why was the policy criticized?</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a) Indirect Rule is a British system of ruling her colonies with the use of local chiefs, or other appointed intermediaries, and traditional laws and customs with British officials merely supervising the administration</p><p>(b) (i) The indirect Rule system excluded the educated elite from participating in the administration.</p><p>(ii) indirect Rule guaranteed the position of chiefs and therefore began to disregard the in-built traditional checks and balances they were subjected to before colonial rule</p><p>(iii) Indirect Rule did little to encourage traditional institutions to develop since colonial officials formulated policies and they only carried, out these policies.</p><p>(iv) The British had had absolute powers to create, recognized and depose traditional leaders which were. powers hitherto exercised by African subjects.</p><p>(v)Indirect Rule introduced certain practices alien to Africans e.g the appointment of warrant chiefs.</p><p>(vi) Imposition of taxes made indirect Rule unpopular •</p><p>(vii) Indirect Rule introduced Divide and Rule tactics</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 11,
        "year": 2013,
        "question": "<p>What factors have governed Nigeria's relations with her neighboring states?</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(i) <strong>Geography:</strong> Nigeria is bordered on three sides (north, west, North east and east) by Niger, Chad, Cameroon and Benin Republic. Because of this physical proximity, she is able to relate with them amicably.</p><p>(ii) <strong>Culture:</strong> The neighboring countries share the same culture and ethnicity with some States in Nigeria. The colonial artificial boundaries in many instances cut villages into two. Nevertheless, official languages differ i.e. English for Nigeria and French for Niger, Chad, Benin Republic excerpt Cameroon which is bilingual.</p><p>(iii) <strong>Economic:</strong> Trade activities with her neighbors strengthened their economic ties.</p><p>(iv) <strong>Security:</strong> Instability in all the neighboring countries has had repercussions Nigeria and vice versa.</p><p>(v) Common membership of international organizations</p><p>(vi) Natural disasters like flood, drought, etc.</p><p>(viii) Cross-border crimes</p><p>(ix) Bilateral agreements </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 12,
        "year": 2013,
        "question": "<p>(a) identify any four past Secretaries-General of the United Nations Organisation (UNO)</p><p>(b) State any five functions of the Secretary-General of the United Nations Organisation</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a) (i) Gladwyn Jebb</p><p>(ii) Trygve Lie</p><p>(iii) Dag Hammarskjold</p><p>(iv) U-Thant</p><p>(v) Kurt Waldheim</p><p>(iv) Javier Perez De Cuellar</p><p>(vii) Boutros Boutros Ghali</p><p>(viii) Kofi Annan</p><p>(b) (i) The Secretary-General brings any matter that threatens world peace to the attention of the Security Council.</p><p>(ii) He prepares annual report for the General Assembly</p><p>(iii) He prepares the agenda for the meeting of the General Assembly and Security Council</p><p>(iv) He appoints other members of staff in the Secretariat</p><p>(v) He administers peace keeping operations world-wide</p><p>(vi) He coordinates the activities of the other organs of the United Nations</p><p>(vii) He supervises the work of the Secretariat.</p><p>(viii) He furnishes the world media with relevant information on the activities of the UNO</p><p>(ix) He oversees the preparation of the UNO budget </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    }
]